Finding Aid for Leonard K. Eaton papers, 1950-2004
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Leonard K. Eaton papers 1950-2004
Eaton, Leonard K., 1922-
1 oversize folders
4.5 linear feet
8910 Aa/2; UAm
Professor of architectural history at the University of Michigan. Correspondence, topical files, college term papers written by Eaton, papers written by Eaton students (mainly concerning the architecture of Michigan buildings), and photographs; subjects include seventeenth century Dutch architecture, the Chicago school of architecture, and the career of Frank Lloyd Wright. Also included is Eaton's research file on the Palmer-Ryan House designed by Frank Lloyd Wright in Ann Arbor. The collection contains extensive correspondence with architect William Gray Purcell
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mr. Eaton (donor no. 7547 ), April 1988; additional material was transferred from the U-M Art and Architecture Library in 1996. Further materials were donated by Mr. Eaton in 2004.
No further additions to the records are expected.
The collection is open to research.
Leonard K. Eaton was born in Minneapolis, Minnesota on February 3, 1922 and served as a faculty member of the College of Architecture and Urban Planning at the University of Michigan from 1950 to 1988. He graduated cum laude, Phi Beta Kappa from Williams College in 1943. From 1943 to 1945, he served with the 10th Mountain Division during World War II. After the war, he did graduate work in history under Arthur M. Schlesinger, Sr. at Harvard, receiving his doctorate in 1950. His dissertation, entitled New England Hospitals, 1790-1833, was published by the University of Michigan Press in 1957.
In 1950, Eaton joined the faculty of the University of Michigan as an instructor in architectural history, becoming a full professor in 1963. Shortly after his arrival in Ann Arbor, Eaton became involved in city zoning issues and proposals for city planning commissions.
Eaton became known as an authority on Frank Lloyd Wright and other figures of the Chicago school of architecture. He was involved with organizing Frank Lloyd Wright symposiums at the University of Michigan, promoting research on Wright architecture in Michigan, and writing reviews of books on Wright. In 1969, Eaton published his book entitled Two Chicago architects and their clients: Frank Lloyd Wright and Howard Van Doren. Eaton also wrote a book on the history of the Palmer House in Ann Arbor, which was never published.
Other books published by Eaton include: American architecture comes of age: European reaction to H.H. Richardson and Louis Sullivan (1972), The architecture of Samuel Maclure (1971), Landscape artist in American: the life and work of Jens Jensen (1964), and Readings in architectural criticism (1954).
Eaton was a member of the Society of Architectural Historians as well as the Canadian Society of Architectural Historians.
The Leonard K. Eaton papers document his career as a professor of architectural history at the University of Michigan and reflect his interest in seventeenth-century Dutch architecture and the Chicago school of architecture. The papers cover the years 1950-1988 and reflect Eaton's activities as architectural historian, student advisor, author, and participant in architectural professional groups.
The Eaton papers have come to the library in three accessions. The first in 1988 came from Mr. Eaton; the second in 1996 consisted of materials that he had donated to the University of Michigan Art and Architecture Library and which they subsequently transferred to the Bentley Library. The third accession contained some topical files and material related to the Palmer House in Ann Arbor. The first accession has been retained in its original order and consists of five series: Correspondence, Topical Files, College Term Papers written by Leonard Eaton, Student Papers written by Eaton Students, and Photographs
The Correspondence series is arranged alphabetically and consists mainly of outgoing letters. Of special interest is the exchange of letters with Lewis Mumford dating from the late 1950s. Topical Files consists of notes and drafts of Eaton's published articles, which have been arranged by title. Also included in this series are articles relating to the landscape architect Jens Jensen as well as notes and published writings from the 2004 accession. College Term Papers written by Eaton series is arranged alphabetically. Mainly undated, these papers reflect Eaton's interest in literature, art and political theory. Student papers written by Eaton students series focuses on Michigan buildings and architecture. The Photographs series includes photographs used in his research on Dutch architecture and a Flint, Michigan, public housing project.
Subjects:
Architects.; Architecture--Michigan.; Architecture--History.; Chicago school of architecture (Movement); Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Holland (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Manchester (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; University of Michigan. College of Architecture and Urban Planning.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Wright, Frank Lloyd, 1867-1959.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Palmer-Ryan House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Buildings, structures, etc.; Purcell, William Gray, 1880-1965.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Architecture.; Buildings--Michigan--Flint.; Buildings--Michigan--Grand Rapids.; Buildings--Michigan--Holland.; Buildings--Michigan--Manchester.; Flint (Mich.)--Buildings.; Grand Rapids (Mich.)--Buildings.; Holland (Mich.)--Buildings.; Manchester (Mich.)--Buildings.; Palmer-Ryan House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Wright, Frank Lloyd, 1867-1959.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Buildings.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Biographical/Personal
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - 1950-1974, 37 folders (Box 1)
  - 1975-1985, 27 folders (Box 2)
  - 1986-1988, 7 folders (Box 3)
- Topical files
  - AIA Journal article, 1971 (Box 3)
    (includes photos and printed matter)
  - Newspaper article clippings (Box 3)
  - Progressive Architecture article, 1958-1959 (Box 3)
    (includes photos)
  - Sullivan article 1958 (Box 3)
  - Sullivan-Berlage article 1956 (Box 3)
  - Two Chicago architects (drawings from book), 1969 (Box 3)
  - Winnipeg/ Urban Review article, 1982 (Box 3)
    (includes architectural plan and photos)
  - Eaton's Published Writings 1964, 2000 (Box 3)
  - Jens Jensen Articles 1991-2004 (Box 3)
  - Notes on Japanese Gardens (Box 3)
- College Term Papers written by LKE
  - Impressionist elements in the work of Stephen Crane and Winslow Homer (Box 3)
  - Thomas Shepard: A Study in Puritan Style (Box 3)
  - The Use of History in the Political Theory of Hobbes and Harrington (1947) (Box 3)
  - Winslow Homer: American artist at war (Box 3)
- Student Papers by LKE Students
  (most includes photographs)
  - Andringa, Gordon. The Dutch settlement in Michigan 1964 (Box 3)
  - Daverman, Robert. Frank Lloyd Wright/Grand Rapids 1975 (Box 3)
  - Kimble, David. The Manchester Project 1983 (Box 3)
  - Kimble, David. Domestic examples of brick vernacular architecture in Manchester township 1984 (Box 3)
  - Northrup, A. Dale. Frank Lloyd Wright in Michigan 1968 (Box 3)
  - Palguta, Lynn. Italian villa vernacular 1983 (Box 3)
    (includes Ann Arbor building)
  - Pyne, Kathleen. Influence of Frank Lloyd Wright and the Prairie School in Grand Rapids 1975 (Box 3)
  - Siefert, Karen and Karen Keating. Grand Rapids architecture (untitled paper) (Box 3)
  - Stellrecht, Kim. Two architects and three houses (Box 3)
  - Waters, John. Gordon Lloyd and the Gothic Revival in Michigan 1987 (Box 3)
    (includes St. Andrew's Episcopal Church, Ann Arbor, Michigan)
- Photographs
  - From "Report from Amsterdam" Progressive Architecture, February 1976 (Box 3)
  - From article on a public housing project in Flint, Michigan April 19, 1969 (Box 3)
- Miscellaneous research files
  The Miscellaneous Files series (received in the 1996 accession) consists of collected materials gathered by Eaton in the course of his research on architectural history themes. Of note is an extensive exchange of correspondence with architect William Gray Purcell. Covering the years 1951-1960, this file includes letters exchanged as well as collected materials (published and visual) relating in part to the career of Purcell. Smaller files consist of collected information on the topic of warehouses and industrial buildings (mainly relating to the Leonard Construction Co.) about which Eaton wrote in Gateway Cities and Other Essays. The Gateway Cities and Other Essays file - consists of those essays written by LKE and selected for inclusion in his Gateway book but ultimately omitted from the published volume.
  - William Gray Purcell files 1951-1960
    - Correspondence and collected materials (published and visual) relating in part to the career of Purcell, 99 folders (Box 4)
  - Warehouses and industrial buildings
    - Collected published information mainly relating to the Leonard Construction Co., 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Gateway Cities and Other Essays
    - Essays written by LKE and selected for inclusion in Gateway book but omitted from published volume (Box 4)
- Palmer House Book Project
  The Palmer House Book Project series consists of materials relating to the Palmer House designed by Frank Lloyd Wright in Ann Arbor and the book Eaton wrote on the subject. Included are interviews with the Palmers, correspondence and copies of correspondence between the Palmers, Eaton, and Frank Lloyd Wright, draft versions of the book, newspaper articles on the house, and photographs.
  - Research
    - Interviews, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Correspondence
      - Palmer-Wright, 2 folders (Box 5)
      - Palmer-Eaton (Box 5)
    - Notes on Palmer House (Box 5)
  - Manuscript Sections
    - Chronology (Box 5)
    - Draft of Introduction (Box 5)
    - Draft of Garden Chapter (Box 5)
    - Draft Sections (Box 5)
    - Complete Manuscript (Box 5)
  - Publicity
    - Newspaper Articles (Box 5)
    - Michigan Society of Architects Bulletin containing photographs of Palmer House (Box 5)
  - Photographs
    - Palmer House photographs (Box 5)
    - Palmer House photographs (Folder 1)